בקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is צדיק זיין Tzaddik Zayin
97 and we pick up
at צדיק
ו עמוד ב Tzaddik Vav Amud Bet five lines from the bottom.
תנו רבנן. Tano Rabbanan. Okay, so we've been discussing all yesterday how
we know various aspects about carrying as a מלאכה melacha and the
various different ways, and some of it we basically more than anything
else needed explicit פסוקים psukim or explicit traditions. And in that discussion
there was an issue about whether צלפחד Tzelafchad was what his sin
was when he was, sorry, not צלפחד, Tzelafchad, whether the מקושש Mekoshesh
was, what did he do? Was it carrying? Was it gathering? Was
it uprooting? Now we continue with that discussion of the מקושש. Mekoshesh.
So, five lines from the bottom.
תנו רבנן, Tano Rabbanan, מקושש זה צלפחד. Mekoshesh Zeh Tzelafchad. That was
צלפחד. Tzelafchad. וכן הוא אומר V'chen Hu Omer and it says ויהיו
בני ישראל במדבר וימצאו איש, Vayihyu Bnei Yisrael Bamidbar Vayimtzeu Ish, they
were in the wilderness and they found a man מקושש עצים. Mekoshesh
Etzim. ולהלן הוא אומר אבינו מת במדבר, U'lehalan Hu Omer Avinu Met
Bamidbar,
our father died. So במדבר במדבר, Bamidbar Bamidbar, גזרה שוה. Gzeirah Shava.
I mean, that's such a rare word in the תורה. Torah.
So מה להלן צלפחד אף כאן צלפחד דברי רבי עקיבא, Ma Lahalan
Tzelafchad Af Kan Tzelafchad Divrei Rabbi Akiva, that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva said.
Now, this is in general חז"ל's Chazal desire to, you know, tie
up loose ends and to identify unnamed people with other named people
in the תורה. Torah. So that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does.
אמר לו רבי יהודה בן בתירה, Amar Lo Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beteira,
so רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beteira said to him,
עקיבא, Akiva, בין כך ובין כך אתה עתיד ליתן את הדין. Bein
Kach U'vein Kach Atah Atid Liten Et Hadin. Whether you're right or
wrong, you're going to pay for having said this. אם כדבריך התורה
כסתהו ואתה מגלה אותו. Im Kidvarecha HaTorah Kissato V'atah Megaleh Oto. If
you're right,
the תורה Torah covered it up, wanted to protect his honor, and
you are revealing it. So what right do you have to do
this? ואם לאו, V'im Lav, and if not, if you're wrong, אתה
מוציא לעז על אותו צדיק, Atah Motzi La'az Al Oto Tzaddik, then
you're spreading an evil report on a righteous person. Okay, so either
way, what's the point of saying something like this? אלא, Ela, says
the גמרא, Gemara, הגמר גזרה שוה. Hagmar Gzeirah Shava.
But okay, but at the end of the day רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva had a גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava so what's he supposed to
do? The גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava teaches him this, what is he
not supposed to say it? רש"י Rashi says it a little bit
even more clearly, ואלא גמר גזרה שוה אם כן לא כסתהו התורה
שויה ליה כמפורש, V'ela Gamar Gzeirah Shava Im Kein Lo Chissato HaTorah
Shavei Leh K'meforash,
then it's not that the תורה Torah hid it. If the תורה
Torah gave you the גזרה שוה, Gzeirah Shava, then it basically wanted
you to explain it. I mean, how is it then anything else
that חז"ל Chazal דרשן? darshan? So the גמרא Gemara says גזרה שוה
לא גמר. Gzeirah Shava Lo Gamar. No,
רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda Ben Beteira didn't hold of the
גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava so he was not impressed with רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. Okay, but still doesn't exactly explain what the challenge was
to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had the גזרה
שוה, Gzeirah Shava, so,
and תוספות Tosafot has another interesting question. תוספות Tosafot says, ואם תאמר
ולגמור מרבי עקיבא. V'im Tomar V'ligmor MeRabbi Akiva.
Not having a tradition is different than having the, having an opposing
tradition. You just don't have it. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had
a tradition. Maybe you should learn from רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that
that is what, that that's a genuine גזרה שוה. Gzeirah Shava. שהוא
קבלה מרבו, Shehu Kibla MeRabbo, שהיו להם בקבלה מנין גזרה שוה שבכל
התורה וזו היתה יתירה על החשבון. Shehayu Lahem Bekabbala Minyan Gzeirah Shava
Shebechol HaTorah V'zo Hayta Yetira Al Hacheshbon. No,
he actually had an opposing, as it were,
tradition. He knew that this was not among the גזרות שוות. Gzeirot
Shavot. Okay, which raises all these interesting questions, right, about exactly what
it means that a גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava is known by tradition
and how the גמרא Gemara can sort of challenge why do you
make a גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava this way, why not make it
that way? So the ראשונים Rishonim already discuss some of those issues,
like the רמב"ן Ramban is bothered when the גמרא Gemara says you
know well why do you make a גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava from
these פסוקים? psukim? It's a better link to make it from those
פסוקים. psukim. And the רמב"ן Ramban says what type of question is
that? It's all tradition. He says well it must be the tradition
was, let's say they knew the הלכה halacha and they knew the
idea that there was a גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava behind it, but
the exact specifics of the גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava was left for
them to figure out. So there are all these interesting questions about
it. It's also interesting to think that there was this idea of
a tradition of a גזרה שוה Gzeirah Shava that was just really
for אגדתא Aggadata purposes. But anyway, so, but that is an issue
that בן בתירה Ben Beteira was not impressed with this desire of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva to link it to צלפחד. Tzelafchad. Now the
גמרא Gemara goes on in a similar way. אלא מהיכא הוה, Ela
Meheicha Hava,
so where was, so who was this, what was the sin of
צלפחד Tzelafchad that it says והוא בחטאו מת, V'hu B'cheto Met, he
died with his sin? Right, that's also probably what is very sort
of suggestive to חז"ל, Chazal, like, which sin? His sin? That's interesting.
What was his sin? So, ויעפילו. Vayapilu. Yes, thank you, thank you
Michael, yes. Okay, so אלא מהיכא הוה, Ela Meheicha Hava, where was
it from? ויעפילו. Vayapilu. He was one of the people that were
insistent to go up to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael after the חטא
המרגלים. Chet HaMeraglim. So in both of these cases it seems to
be trying to make him like, you know, it wasn't just a
mundane sin or it wasn't an evil sin, it was a type
of a sin that came ultimately in some type of a religious
context. So presumably the purpose of the one, although it didn't say
it but elsewhere we hear, you know, that the idea of the
מקושש Mekoshesh was or צלפחד Tzelafchad was to
demonstrate...
Well yeah I mean not exactly true you know either way you
could say חטאו כיסתו, Chatas kisato, right? And what are you going
to be מגלה אותו? m'galeh oso? Right. Okay, I mean that's a
question. But anyway, but I think what's important to note here is
that you know that the גמרא Gemara is trying to identify, right,
where is it?
Right,
right, right. So right, so ויהיו בני ישראל במדבר וימצאו איש מקושש
עצים Vayehyu Bnei Yisroel bamidbar vayimtzu ish mekoshesh eitzim occurs right right
after the חטא המרגלים. Cheis Ham'raglim. So what is it doing right
after the חטא המרגלים? Cheis Ham'raglim? Also, by the way, right after
the חטא המרגלים Cheis Ham'raglim was right, the person ויעפילו לעלות ההרה,
Vayapilu la'alos hahora, the one who tried to you know go, no
I'm
sorry, right במדבר י"ד. Bamidbar Yud Dalet. Right, right after the חטא
המרגלים Cheis Ham'raglim was when God told them you know you can't
go into the land and then a group tried to go into
the land. So interestingly, both of those happen at the end and
in the middle and the end of שלח, Shelach, right after the
חטא המרגלים. Cheis Ham'raglim.
So you know it could act,
so what do you call it?
So sorry, sorry, okay fine. Right, so both of those happen right
after the חטא המרגלים. Cheis Ham'raglim. So both of those also are
a type of a sin that's a sin which has, you know,
you could sort of say a positive religious motivation. The ויעפילו לעלות
ההרה Vayapilu la'alos hahora is thinking like oh, in the end we
sinned, let's try to get things back to the way they were
and let's try to go into the ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. So
at least it's sort of motivated ultimately by that.
And you know even though משה Moshe says God will not be
with you, but still you know they're trying to essentially you know
do תשובה teshuvah and reverse their sin, even though it's a little
bit wrong-headed and get back to the way things were. And the
idea of the מקושש mekoshesh in another elsewhere we're told that the
purpose of it was that people thought, oh now that the חטא
המרגלים Cheis Ham'raglim we're not going into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, maybe
it means like the ברית bris is no longer binding and maybe
we don't have to do the מצוות mitzvos or we won't be
punished for our עבירות, aveiros, you know now that we're not going
into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel. So the מקושש mekoshesh got up to
demonstrate, look, no, everything is binding. I'm going to be מחלל שבת
m'chalel Shabbos and they'll put me to death, and so it just
proves that you know, even though you're not going in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisroel, everything is still in in effect. It's not here, it's
elsewhere that's like how it's explained why the positive motivation of the
מקושש mekoshesh especially if he's identified with צלפחד. Tzelofchad. So the גמרא
Gemara doesn't say that here, but it is worth sort of noting
you know that that might be sort of partly of what's sort
of motivating sort of trying to identify it, but identify it in
a positive frame, although again the גמרא Gemara didn't say it here
about the issue of the מקושש mekoshesh but elsewhere it does. And
it is interesting to note that both of these come immediately after
the מרגלים. meraglim. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues כיוצא בדבר, kiyotze badavar, similarly אתה אומר ata omer
you say ויחר אף ה' בם וילך, Vayichar af Hashem bam vayelech,
similarly to this debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and בן בתירא.
Ben Beteira. It says after you know אהרן Aaron and מרים Miriam
talk about משה, Moshe, God got angry with them and he departed,
and then והנה מרים מצרעת כשלג, Vehinei Miriam metzora'as kashaleg, מרים Miriam
was leprous like snow. מלמד שאף אהרן נצטרע, Melamed she'af Aaron nitztara,
even אהרן Aaron was became leprous not just מרים, Miriam, דברי רבי
עקיבא, divrei Rabbi Akiva, that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. אמר
לו רבי יהודה בן בתירא, Amar lo Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira, so
רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira said, עקיבא, Akiva, בין
כך ובין כך אתה עתיד ליתן את הדין, bein kach u'vein kach
ata asid litein es hadin, whether you're right or wrong you're going
to pay for saying such a thing. אם כדבריך, im k'divarecha, if
you're right that אהרן Aaron got צרעת, tzara'as, התורה כיסתו, Hatorah kisaso,
for some reason the Torah didn't want, wanted to respect, you know,
didn't want to publicize it by אהרן, Aaron, and the Torah covered
it up, ואתה מגלה אותו, v'ata m'galeh oso, and you're uncovering it.
ואם לאו, v'im lav, and if not, אתה מוציא לעז על אותו
צדיק, ata motzi la'az al oso tzaddik, then you're spreading evil report
about אהרן Aaron that he was deserving צרעת. tzara'as. You know, not
like there he was totally right, obviously God got angry, but if
he wasn't deserving צרעת, tzara'as, what are you doing saying that he
was? והא כתיב בם, Veha kesiv bam, doesn't it say that God
got angry against them? So what, so what did that mean? חפנת
נזיפה בם, chofnas nezifa bam, fine, it was like, you know, angry
like, you know, like yelling at them, but it didn't mean that
actually it translated into leprosy into צרעת. tzara'as. That was only with
מרים. Miriam. תני כמאן דאמר אף אהרן נצטרע, Tani k'man d'omar af
Aaron nitztara, we taught like the person approach that said that even
אהרן Aaron got צרעת, tzara'as, דכתיב ויפן אהרן אל מרים והנה מצרעת.
d'chtiv vayifen Aaron el Miriam vehinei metzora'as. אהרן Aaron turned to מרים
Miriam and behold she was leprous, she had צרעת. tzara'as. תנא, tana,
so what does it mean he turned? שפנה מצרעתו, shepana mitzoroso, he
turned away from his צרעת tzara'as to look at her צרעת, tzara'as,
so you see that. Or רש"י Rashi says שפנה מצרעתו, shepana mitzoroso,
רש"י Rashi says קדם ונתרפא, kadam venisrapa, that first it was he
turned, his צרעת tzara'as turned away from him, after his, his צרעת
tzara'as was momentary, he had צרעת tzara'as and then it departed. And
after it departed from him he looked at מרים Miriam and she
still had the צרעת. tzara'as. So according to this approach, he, he
had צרעת tzara'as but it was more, it was briefer. Okay, so
anyway there's an interesting debate where רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva trying at
least in the first case to tie up loose ends, who was
the מקושש, mekoshesh, in the second case it's not clear what he's
trying to do but elsewhere you know it's some there implicit. seem
to be here and elsewhere I think to, I forget who is
it as it says נזיפה, nezifa, ויצא, vayeitzei, not נזיפה, nezifa, excuse
me, ויחר אף השם vayichar af Hashem is normally translates means there
were when there's חרון אף charon af it translates to some sense
of רושם, roshem, right? some consequence. So Rabbi Akiva's trying to tie
up those loose ends and then Ben Beteira is not impressed, although,
again in the first case about the about about what's called?
about צלפחד, Tzelofchad, it does he, you know, it doesn't seem not
clear
that that it was Ben Beteira who did it, but the Gemara
still tries to tie up a loose end and trying to connect
him at least to the ויפילו. Vayapilu. Ben Beteira seems like he's
not into interested in addressing it at all, the Torah's not saying
it, it's not for us to say. Okay.
Yeah, when the Gemara said before אלא מהיכא הוה מויפילו, ela meheicha
hava mivayapilu, that's not Ben Beteira talking, that's the Gemara. You can
see by the shift to the Aramaic. Okay, so Ben Beteira's not
interested in doing this type of activity, but the Gemara is.
Why, I don't know.
No, מהיכא הוה meheicha hava is the Gemara asking, who was this,
who was this, what was the sin of, what was the sin
of צלפחד? Tzelofchad? Okay, yes.
Interesting imagery that all three then would have had an experience with
צרעת. tzara'at.
Oh, Moshe as well. That's a very good point. And actually the
Gemara is about to turn to the צרעת tzara'at of Moshe. So
that's a very good point.
I know. Okay, right. So we're going to turn to that right
now. Okay. So moving on. So אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish,
החושד בכשרים לוקה בגופו. hachoshed biksherim lokeh begufo. Somebody who suspects people
who are innocent of the whatever they're being suspected of, the person
who suspects them, you know, is smitten on his body, on his
very body. דכתיב, dechativ, the verse says והן לא יאמינו לי. vehein
lo ya'aminu li. Moshe says to God, they won't believe in me,
בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, כי יאמרו לא נראה אליך השם. ki yomru
lo nira eilecha Hashem. And
you know as soon as Moshe goes back and immediately their response
is ויאמן העם, vaya'amen ha'am, the people did believe in Moshe. They
might not have had the courage to stand by their belief and
convictions because you know one of the great Rashis of last week's
parsha is that it says you know Moshe and and everybody went
to Pharaoh and then it ends by saying in was just Moshe
and Aaron. So it says you know they were walking and then
as they turned back and who you know you know me and
all everybody here, everybody who? And then you look back and anyway,
but okay, maybe they didn't have the courage to stand by their
convictions, but at least they believed. So and Moshe says they won't
believe. וגליא קמי קודשא בריך הוא, vagalya kamei Kudsha Brich Hu, it's
revealed to God, דמהימני ישראל, demeheimni Yisrael, that Yisrael did would believe.
אמר לו, amar lo,
so God said to Moshe, הם מאמינים בני מאמינים, heim ma'aminim bnei
ma'aminim, they are trustworthy, the children of trustworthy people, which also might
be an allusion to the beginning of next week's parsha, right? וארא
אל אברהם אל יצחק ואל יעקב באל שדי ושמי השם, va'eira el
Avraham el Yitzchak ve'el Ya'akov be'Eil Shadai ushmi Hashem, right? That Moshe
says, you know, God you promised and you're not fulfilling. And God
says, you know, ah look, I appeared to Avraham, Yitzchak, and Ya'akov
and you know again the Rashi there says you know you know
another great Rashi, אוי חבל על דאבדין ולא משתכחין, oy chaval al
de'avdin velo mishtakchin, right? Woe to you know the past generations, they
I promised them, they believed in me even though it wasn't fulfilled
right away. And here you're already starting to doubt me. So again,
so here God is saying they are מאמינים בני מאמינים, ma'aminim bnei
ma'aminim, you know, the sons of Avraham, Yitzchak, and Ya'akov. ואתה סופך
לא להאמין, ve'atah sofcha lo leha'amin, in the end you won't have
the full
belief. הם מאמינים דכתיב ויאמן העם, heim ma'aminim dechativ vaya'amen ha'am, they
are the people had belief as soon as Moshe reported it. בני
מאמינים, bnei ma'aminim, the children of those who had faith, ויאמין בהשם,
vaya'amin baHashem, by Avraham. אתה סופך לא להאמין, atah sofcha lo leha'amin,
you in the end we won't be able to say that you
had אמונה. emunah. שנאמר יען לא האמנתם בי. shene'emar ya'an lo he'emantem
bi. All three notice it's not just the theme, it's the word
האמין, he'emin, right? And by Aaron and Moshe when they sin by
the מי מריבה, Mei Merivah, it says because you did not have
faith in me, האמנתם בי. he'emantem bi.
האמנתם בי, he'emantem bi, because others
have it's the same word,
האמין, he'emin, האמנתם. he'emantem. ממאי דלקה, mimai delaka, how do you know
that Moshe was smitten? דכתיב ויאמר לו השם עוד הבא נא ידך
בחיקך, dechativ vayomer lo Hashem od hava na yadcha becheikecha, because look
what happens, he got צרעת. tzara'at. So you see so it's a
very lovely tight midrash that does two things, right? It plays with
the word יאמינו, ya'aminu, הם לא יאמינו, heim lo ya'aminu, ויאמן העם,
vaya'amen ha'am, and Moshe himself didn't in another place says לא האמנתם.
lo he'emantem. And it gives this connection to the purpose of the
צרעת. tzara'at. By the way, in both places what the Gemara's also
not saying is it could have just said לשון הרע. lashon hara.
Miriam speaks לשון הרע, lashon hara, she got צרעת. tzara'at. Moshe is
speaking לשון הרע lashon hara on בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, right? And
he got צרעת. tzara'at. But it's interesting here the shift is not
the צרעת tzara'at and לשון הרע, lashon hara, but if you are
חושד choshed in somebody else. And of course there's a power, you
know, you suspect somebody so basically it really you know even if
it really gets to the very that's the whole problem about לשון
הרע lashon hara is about the reputation and how you think about
somebody central to a person's sort of, you know, identity and the
things you associate with them, their character. So you think about certain
things and you suspect them. So you know, how that gives that
gives physical the sort of מידה כנגד מידה mida kineged mida is
something happens to you yourself in a very physical way and therefore
it is this צרעת. tzara'at.
Okay.
אמר רבא ואיתימא רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, amar Rava ve'iseima Rabbi Yosi
be'Rabbi Chanina, מדה טובה ממהרת mida tova memaheret פורעניות. puranios. A good,
the good attribute, meaning God's sort of reward for the good, comes
quicker than the punishment for the bad. תדע דהא במידה פורעניות, T'da
d'ha b'mida puranios, when it was bad, the sense of paying for
the bad,
כתיב ketiv ויוציאה והנה ידו מצורעת כשלג. Vayotzi'ah vehine yado metzorat kasheleg.
When Moshe took his hand out of his chest, behold it was
מצורעת metzorat like snow. ואילו במידה טובה Ve'ilu be'mida tova when God
was doing good,
כתיב ketiv and God returned it to its flesh color,
ויוציאה מחיקו והנה שבה כבשרו. Vayotzi'ah mecheiko vehine shava kevisaro. So and
it returned. מחיקו הוא דשבה כבשרו, Mecheiko hu de'shava kevisaro, as soon
as he removed it from his chest, even before he had fully
taken it out of his clothes, it had already returned to the
flesh color. So it returned to the flesh quicker
than when it turned leprous. Okay, now that we're talking about Moshe,
Aharon and so on, or Moshe, we'll have one other quick
דרשה: drasha: ויבלע מטה אהרן את מטותם, Vayivla mateh Aharon et matotam,
the end here because we're talking
about Moshe at the סנה sneh and then going and speaking to
בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So one of
the loose ends there is so Moshe speaks to בני ישראל, Bnei
Yisrael, so we already discussed ויאמן העם, va'ya'amen ha'am, and then he
demonstrates it to
פרעה, Paroh, he gives a sign. So although again as רש"י Rashi
points out, when God gave Moshe the signs at the סנה, sneh,
they were signs for בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, they weren't the signs
for פרעה, Paroh, but anyway, that somewhat is the culmination of that
arc. So now we talk one sentence about that. It says Aharon's
staff swallowed their staffs. אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar נס בתוך
נס, nes betoch nes, a miracle within a miracle, because it says
the staff swallowed their staffs. So even after it had returned to
looking like a staff, even when it wasn't a נחש, nachash, it
swallowed them. Okay, so that was a nice little digression and actually
very interestingly tying into this week's פרשה. parsha. Back to the halakhic
discussion. רשות היחיד לרשות היחיד. Reshut hayachid lereshut hayachid. So now we're
going from private domain to private domain with the רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim in the middle and it's above ten טפחים. tefachim. And you
throw, oh I'm sorry, not above ten טפחים, tefachim, it says we'll
discuss that. You throw it. You throw it from, the משנה Mishnah
says you throw from a private domain to a private domain with
רשות הרבים reshut harabbim in the middle. Rabbi Akiva says you're חייב
chayav and the חכמים Chachamim say you're פטור. patur. And here the
גמרא Gemara wants to understand what the debate is because remember at
the end of the משנה, Mishnah, it spoke about handing something, מושיט,
moshit, from one רשות היחיד reshut hayachid to another on the same
side of a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. And that was a special
category of obligation. So when Rabbi Akiva says you're חייב chayav for
throwing, is it just because for him that's an extension of the
idea of מושיט, moshit, of that idea of handing, remember from one
balcony to the next? Or is he saying you're חייב chayav for
totally different reason? So that's what the גמרא Gemara asks. Let's see
the
גמרא. Gemara. בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, Rava asked: למטה מעשרה פליגי? Lematta
me'asara pligi? Maybe they're debating when you throw it through רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim within ten טפחים? tefachim? ובהא פליגי, Ubehai pligi, this is
the debate: דמר סבר אמרינן קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא. Demar savar amrinan
kluta k'mi she'huncha damya. Rabbi Akiva says once it enters the air
space of רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, it's like it's on the ground.
So it has nothing to do with this special idea of handing
beams from one wagon to the next and from one רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid to the next. It's the normal הלכה halakha of carrying
from a private domain to a public, from רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
to רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. His point is though even though it
was flying through the air space, since it was within ten טפחים
tefachim and within the air space, it's like it hit the ground.
That's Rabbi Akiva. ומר סבר לא אמרינן קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא. Umar
savar lo amrinan kluta k'mi she'huncha damya. We don't
say that. אבל למעלה מעשרה, Aval lema'ala me'asara,
above ten, דברי הכל פטור. divrei hakol patur. Everybody would have said
you're exempt because above ten is not
the air space of רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. The only way you
could be חייב chayav above ten is if you make it similar
to this case of מושיט, moshit, this special case of one balcony
to the next. And that nobody would say, ולא ילפינן זורק ממושיט.
velo yafinan zorek mimoshit. We do not learn out throwing from handing.
Okay, so there's this one special case of מושיט, moshit, one balcony
to the next. That's limited to actually handing over. Throwing, nobody would
apply it to there. The issue is when it's within ten טפחים,
tefachim, is it like it's on the ground of רשות הרבים? reshut
harabbim? That's one way of discussing it. או דילמא, Ode dilma, or
do we say, למעלה מעשרה פליגי? lema'ala me'asara pligi? No, they're arguing
when it's above ten טפחים. tefachim. ובהא פליגי, Ubehai pligi, and this
is what they're debating: דמר סבר ילפינן זורק
ממושיט. Demar savar yafinan zorek mimoshit. The same way handing from one
balcony to the next is חייב, chayav, Rabbi Akiva would say throwing
from one balcony to the next is חייב. chayav. ומר סבר לא
ילפינן זורק ממושיט. Umar savar lo yafinan zorek mimoshit. No, only handing,
it's a very special case and not throwing. אבל למטה מעשרה, Aval
lematta me'asara, but under ten, דברי הכל חייב. divrei hakol chayav. Everybody
might say you're חייב. chayav. You could have said דברי הכל פטור,
divrei hakol פטור, but anyway the גמרא Gemara says דברי הכל חייב.
divrei hakol chayav. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? קלוטה כמי
שהונחה דמיא. Kluta k'mi she'huncha damya. Everybody would agree that when it's
in the air space of רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and it's flying
through, it's like it's on the ground. So what is it a
debate? Is it a debate of this special case about מושיט, moshit,
or is it a general debate about carrying and within the air
space of רשות הרבים? reshut harabbim? אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef,
הא מילתא איבעיא ליה לרב חסדא. ha milsa ibaya lei l'Rav Chisda.
That exact same question רב חסדא Rav Chisda had. ופשטה ליה לרב
המנונא, Upashta lei l'Rav Hamnuna, and רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna tried to
clarify it for him מהא, meha, from the following ברייתא baraita we
see: מרשות היחיד לרשות היחיד ועובר ברשות הרבים עצמה. Mershut hayachid lereshut
hayachid ve'over bereshut harabbim atzmah. Somebody is going from a private domain
to a private and passing through the רשות הרבים reshut harabbim itself.
רבי עקיבא
מחייב וחכמים פוטרין. Rabbi Akiva mechayev vechachamim potrin. Rabbi Akiva says you're
חייב. chayav. So it's almost exactly the same as our משנה Mishna,
*Mishna*, except rather than saying throwing, it says it says going, מעביר
*ma'avir*, it presumably means walking. So let's take a look. מדקתני רשות
הרבים reshus harabim? עצמה *midekatni Reshut HaRabim Atzmah* and also the fact
it says in the very רשות הרבים reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim*, what's
the point of that extra word עצמה *atzmah*? Why not say רשות
הרבים reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim*? Since it says רשות הרבים reshus harabim
עצמה *Reshut HaRabim Atzmah* itself, so פשיטא Pshita למטה מעשרה פליגי *pshita
lemata me'asarah pligi*.
So it means it's in the air space of רשות הרבים reshus
harabim *Reshut HaRabim*, it's within ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*. ובמאי *ubemai*, and
what's the case? אילימא במעביר *ileima be'ma'avir*, if it's talking about you're
just walking it, and למטה מעשרה הוא דמחייב למעלה מעשרה לא מחייב
mechayev *lemata me'asarah hu de'mechayev lemala me'asarah lo mechayev*, and maybe it's
telling you only because you're within the air space of רשות הרבים
reshus harabim. *Reshut HaRabim*, if you were higher than the air space,
you would be exempt. So maybe it's just talking about walking. If
it's talking about walking, what's the debate? Maybe the debate is, so,
or what's the reason of emphasizing, excuse me,
the רשות הרבים reshus harabim עצמה *Reshut HaRabim Atzmah* within ten טפחים
tefachim *tefachim*? There'd be no reason to emphasize that, דאמר רבי Rebbi
אלעזר *de'amar Rabbi Elazar*, רבי Rebbi אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* says, המוציא משאוי
למעלה מעשרה חייב chayav, שכן משא בני קהת *ha'motzi masoy lemala me'asarah
chayav sheken masa bnei Kehat*. Remember we had that teaching, if you
take it from your private domain and you carry it higher than
the air space of רשות הרבים reshus harabim. *Reshut HaRabim* and then
you stop, it's like you put it down in רשות הרבים reshus
harabim *Reshut HaRabim* and you're actually חייב chayav. *chayav*. So even though
the carrying was over the air space, if in the end it
was placed down within, you're חייב chayav. *chayav*. So here, what would
be the reason if you're carrying it to say you're carrying it
within the air space of רשות הרבים reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim* if
you actually are חייב chayav *chayav* even when you carry higher than
the air space of רשות הרבים reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim*? It doesn't
make sense. אלא לאו *ella lav*, if we're saying it was within
the air space, it must be בזורק *be'zorek*, when you threw it,
not when you carried it. ולמטה מעשרה הוא דמחייב *u'lemata me'asarah hu
de'mechayev*, and you're חייב chayav? *chayav* because it's within ten טפחים tefachim
*tefachim*, למעלה מעשרה לא מחייב *lemala me'asarah lo mechayev*, higher than ten
not. שמע מינה בקלוטה כמי שהונחה פליגי שמע מינה *shma mina bikluta
k'mi she'huncha pligi shma mina*. You see they're arguing not about this
idea of מושיט *moshit*, they're arguing about this idea of when it's
throwing it and going through the air space, is it like it
has come to rest? So again, just to clarify, right, you have
one scenario where you have like the two balconies alongside רשות הרבים
reshus harabim. *Reshut HaRabim* and we learn out from בני קהת *bnei
Kehat* same side that if you hear, here'll be רשות הרבים reshus
harabim, *Reshut HaRabim*, that if you hand it from one to the
other, right, you're going to be חייב chayav *chayav*. So then you
have it like let's say on opposite sides and you know you
could be throw you'd be פטור patur. *patur*, but but maybe if
you throw it you'd be חייב chayav *chayav*. So רבי עקיבא Rebbe
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says if you throw you are חייב chayav *chayav*.
And the question is what are we talking about? Throwing from one
balcony to the next, and it's an extension of this question about
like the handing from one balcony to the next, or generally throwing
in the רשות הרבים reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim*. If it's generally throwing
the balconies are higher than ten טפחים tefachim. *tefachim*. So if they're
discussing this special case of מושיט *moshit*, it would be higher than
ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*. If they're discussing not the special case, could
even be across רשות הרבים reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim*, then it's within
ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* is the issue because that's the air space
and only then would you be חייב chayav *chayav*. So that's the
question. Are they debating is it an extension of the מושיט *moshit*
issue or are they debating the general question of throwing something in
the רשות הרבים reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim*? The way the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* tries to prove what they're debating is we see another ברייתא
*braita* that discusses their debate but uses the word that you that
it was transported in the רשות הרבים reshus harabim. עצמה *Reshut HaRabim
Atzmah*. So in the רשות הרבים reshus harabim עצמה *Reshut HaRabim Atzmah*
can only mean that emphasis of itself within ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*.
So obviously then we are it wouldn't be talking about throwing from
one balcony to the next, that would be higher than רשות הרבים
reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim*. We wouldn't be talking about walking and carrying
it in a רשות הרבים reshus harabim *Reshut HaRabim* because if you're
walking, since your feet are on the ground, even if the object
is higher than ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*, since your feet are on
the ground, you'd also be חייב chayav *chayav*, you wouldn't have to
have the object within ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*. So the only place
it makes sense to say we're discussing is within ten טפחים tefachim?
*tefachim* and not walking, because that's why we have to emphasize within
ten טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*. What would that be? Throwing. So throwing within
ten טפחים tefachim, *tefachim* and you see that is where רבי Rebbi
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and חכמים chachamim *chachamim* are debating. Again, all of
this learned out from that one word of עצמה *atzmah*, that the
scenario that רבי Rebbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* are
in is in the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim, עצמה *Reshut HaRabim Atzmah*,
meaning within ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim*. And therefore the only issue the
only time it matters that it's within ten טפחים tefachim *tefachim* is
when it's being thrown, not carried, and therefore you see they're debating
throwing it within ten טפחים *tefachim*.
The way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
So that's one proof. ופליגא דרבי אלעזר *u'pliga darbi Elazar*, that argues
on רבי Rebbi אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*. דאמר רבי Rebbi אלעזר *de'amar Rabbi
Elazar*, רבי Rebbi, אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* said, מחייב היה רבי Rebbi עקיבא
אפילו למעלה מעשרה *mechayev hayah Rabbi Akiva afilu lemala me'asarah*. And רבי
Rebbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said you're חייב chayav *chayav* for throwing it
even higher than ten. והא דקתני רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. עצמה *v'ha
diktani Reshut HaRabim Atzmah*,
how about again we just made a very good proof that the
debate is the in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim, עצמה *Reshut HaRabim Atzmah*
meaning within ten? להודיעך כחן דרבנן *lehodi'acha kochan de'rabbanan*,
to show you the strength of the Rabbis, meaning they debate both
cases. They debate one case of throwing it within ten that רבי
Rebbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says you're חייב chayav *chayav* because of קלוטה
כמי שהונחה keluta kemi shehuncha, *kluta k'mi she'huncha* and the Rabbis would
say you're exempt, and they debate throwing Higher than ten that רבי
Rebbe עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says you're חייב chayav *hayyav* because of, what
do you call, because of מושיט *moshiat*, because of this idea like
one balcony to the next. Okay, so he's actually saying they argue
both cases. The rabbis exempt both cases. Even if it's within ten
they exempt, so the argument is across the board. ופליגא דרב חלקיא
בר טובי *U-pleiga d'Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi*. This argument's on רב Rav
חלקיא בר טובי *Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi*. דאמר רב חלקיא בר טובי
*D'amar Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi*, תוך שלושה דברי הכל חייב chayav *tokh
shelosha divrei hakol hayyav*. Within three tefachim, everybody says you're חייב chayav
*hayyav* because the idea is within three tefachim it's like it's on
the ground. And interestingly, even though it doesn't stop, even though it's
moving, since it's as if it's touching the ground, that presumably counts
enough as if it has stopped. This, by the way, is an
interesting question about the whole issue about like a baby carriage or
whatever. If something is actually touching the ground and constantly moving, right,
does it need an act of הנחה *hanakha*? So he says actually
it doesn't. If it's been thrown within three tefachim, three tefachim is
לבוד *lavud*, it's like it's on the ground, everybody would say you're
חייב chayiv *hayyav* even though it didn't stop. למעלה מעשרה *L'mala m'asara*,
higher than ten, דברי הכל פטור patur *divrei hakol patur*. That's higher
than the airspace of רשות הרבים reshus harabbim *reshut ha-rabim*. So everybody
would say you're exempt. And we don't learn out from מושיט *moshiat*.
מושיט *Moshiat*, the case of the balconies whatever, is a very special
case. So דברי הכל פטור *divrei hakol patur*. מג' ועד י' *Mi-gimmel
v'ad yud*, from between three and ten, באנו למחלוקת רבי Rebbe עקיבא
ורבנן *banu l'mahloket Rabbi Akiva v'Rabbanan*. That's the debate of רבי Rebbi
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and the rabbis. So this basically is like the
first position. They only debate within ten. But it actually added another
interesting point that within three even the rabbis would admit, it's like
it's on the ground and even if it doesn't stop, it's like
it came to a rest. So again, we have the emphasis of
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is that the debate is lower than ten
טפחים *tefachim* when it's passing through the airspace. Is it like it's
on the ground? That's learned from the word רשות הרבים reshus harabbim,
*reshut ha-rabim* עצמה *atzma*. If you are carrying it higher, it doesn't
even have to be within ten טפחים *tefachim*, but if it's because
then your feet are within. But if it's being thrown, it has
to be within ten טפחים *tefachim*. That's the debate of whether it
flies through the airspace, is it like it came to rest? Now
we've added the qualification that if it's within three, you don't even
need, everybody would agree, you don't need it to come to a
rest. Okay, so higher than ten is higher than the airspace, everybody
agrees it's not an issue unless you're carrying it. But if you're
throwing it, it's not an issue. Lower than three, it's like it's
on the ground, everybody agrees it's חייב chayiv *hayyav*. The issue is
in the airspace between three and ten. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says the following. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya nami hakhi*, ומסייע
ליה *u-mesaye'a lei*. בתוך ג' דברי הכל חייב chayiv *Betokh gimmel divrei
hakol hayyav*. Thrown within three, everybody says you're חייב chayiv, *hayyav*. למעלה
מעשרה אינו אלא משום שבות *L'mala m'asara eino ela mishum shevut*. Higher
than ten, it's only a rabbinic issue, it's not biblical. ואם היו
רשות שלו מותר mutar. *V'im hayu reshut shelo muttar*. If you own
the property, it's permissible. I'll get back to that in a second.
מג' ועד י' *Mi-gimmel v'ad yud*, from three to ten, that's the
debate. רבי Rebbi עקיבא מחייב וחכמים פוטרים *Rabbi Akiva mehayyev v'Hahamim potrim*.
רבי Rebbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says you're חייב chayiv *hayyav* and the
חכמים *Hahamim* say you are exempt. So the debate is within ten,
whether the airspace is like it's, is like it came to a
rest. Now, what does it mean higher than ten and if it's
your property? I, if I had a house here and a house
here on two opposite ends of the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim *reshut
ha-rabim*, and I threw let's say from one rooftop to the next.
That's the common scenario that they use, their rooftops. So not from
one window to the next, but from one rooftop to the next.
And you said, no, you can't do that, that's an איסור דרבנן
*issur d'rabbanan*. What would you assume the איסור דרבנן *issur d'rabbanan* is?
Throwing from one rooftop on one side of the רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim *reshut ha-rabim* to the other rooftop on
the other side
of the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. *reshut ha-rabim*. Throwing over רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim *reshut ha-rabim*. It's very similar to carrying. What if it
would have fallen down, or it would have hit רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim *reshut ha-rabim*, so it would have been a שוגג shogeg, *shogeg*
or whatever, but you would have gone from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
*reshut ha-yahid* to רשות הרבים reshus harabbim *reshut ha-rabim*. Interestingly, the implication
in the משנה *Mishnah*, in this ברייתא *Baraita*, which the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to explain in a minute, is no. The דרבנן
*d'rabbanan* is you went from one private domain to another private domain.
They could have been next door. And if, what's the הלכה *halakha*,
are you allowed to carry from one private domain to another one?
Only if you do what? Have an עירוב *eiruv*. Not an עירוב
*eiruv* of the תחומי שבת *tehumei Shabbat*, an עירוב חצרות *eiruv hatzerot*,
to make it like it's one domain. Because otherwise it feels like
carrying. Whatever, that's the whole מסכת עירובין *Masechet Eiruvin*. So even when
it's going across the רשות הרבים reshus harabim *reshut ha-rabim*, the only
problem was that these two houses hadn't made an עירוב *eiruv*. And
that's why it says if you own both houses, you're even לכתחילה
*lekhathila* allowed to throw from one rooftop to the next over רשות
הרבים reshus harabim *reshut ha-rabim*, which is wild. Right? רבי Rebbi, עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva* might say, you know, based on one opinion, רבי Rebbi
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* would say that case you're חייב chayiv *hayyav*. But
here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying no, the whole debate is
within ten טפחים *tefachim*, over everybody says you're פטור *patur*, and it
even would be מותר mutar? *muttar* if you own the houses, both
houses. Yes?
So this, so this,
if the roof would be a כרמלית *karmelit* rather than a רשות
*reshut*.
No, the roof is רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshut ha-yahid* because the
walls underneath are seen as extending high, up, up. Oh, so the,
yes, the roof is what is רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshut ha-yahid*.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, let's see. So אמר מר
*Amar mar*.
Where were we? אמר מר, ואם היו רשות שלו *Amar mar, v'im
hayu reshut shelo*, if they're, if they're your houses, מותר *muttar*. לימא
תהוי תיובתא דרב *Leima tehvei tiyuvta d'Rav*? דאיתמר *D'itmar*. Maybe this is
a debate of רב *Rav*, because it said, שני בתים בשני צידי
רשות הרבים reshus harabim *shnei batim bi-shnei tziddei reshut ha-rabim*. Exactly this,
two houses opposite sides of the רשות הרבים reshus harabim, *reshut ha-rabim*.
רבה בר רב הונא אמר רב *Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar Rav*,
אסור assur לזרוק מזה לזה *assur lizrok mi-zeh l'zeh*. You can't throw
from one to the next. ושמואל אמר *u-Shmuel amar*, מותר לזרוק מזה
לזה *muttar lizrok mi-zeh l'zeh*. You can throw from one to the
next. So you see that seems to be explicit that we're saying
here it is allowed to throw to the next to the next.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, let's, let's take a look. Look,
ולאו? No, so רש״י Rashi says it has to be, it's the
שיטה shita of רב would have never said or שמואל Shmuel would
have never said it's מותר. So here you see that there's an
opinion that it's אסור assur even if, right, I mean as Michael
points out, but as רש״י Rashi says, it has to be that
we're talking about they're both your houses. So how come here and
how come there there's an opinion אסור and here we're saying מותר?
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, ולאו מוקימנא לה, velav mookimna
lah, that case is כגון דמידלי חד ומתתפי חד, kigon demidli chad
umitashfi chad, that one of them is high and the other is
low. They're not on a level, like you know, horizontal plane.
And what's the concern? דזמנין דנפל ואתי לאתויי, dezimnin denafal ve'asi le'asuyei,
because then it's much more likely, you know, if you have a
very tall building and a low building, either way you're trying to
throw, there's a much greater likelihood you'll miss and it'll fall down
and then what will happen? You'll go pick it up and you'll
come to carry it. Now רש״י Rashi says, why do you have
to say you're afraid you'll go pick it up and come to
carry it? Why don't you just say you'll have thrown from רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid to a רשות הרבים? reshus harabim, Okay, it'll be
שוגג, but you'll still have done a מלאכה. melacha. So רש״י Rashi
says, no, as we're about to find when we turn the page,
that wouldn't even constitute a מלאכה בשוגג. melacha beshogeg. Why? Because if
the thing doesn't go where you wanted it to go, that's like,
you know, a total case of a לא הויא מחשבתה, lo havya
machshavtah, it's not מלאכת
מחשבת. meleches machsheves. So that's not even having done a מלאכה. melacha.
It didn't go where you wanted it to go. So the concern
though is it'll fall down and then you'll go pick it up
and carry it. Okay, and therefore, when that, if there's a good
likelihood it'll fall down, we won't allow you to do it. But
the surprise is, when they're the same level, we'll allow you to
throw across a רשות הרבים reshus harabim as long as you're higher
than the air space. Now the גמרא Gemara continues, אמר ליה רב
חסדא לרב המנונא, amar lei Rav Chisda leRav Hamnuna, said רב חסדא
Rav Chisda to רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, ואמרי לה רב המנונא לרב
חסדא, ve'amri lah Rav Hamnuna leRav Chisda, or some said the reverse,
מנא הא מילתא דאמרו רבנן, mana ha milta de'amru rabanan, where did
this thing come from that the rabbis say כל פחות מג' כלבוד
דמי? kol pachas mi'gimmel kelavud dami? Anything within three טפחים is like
it's all like connected. It's like it's, you know, that within three
everybody would say you're חייב, chayiv it's like it was on the
ground. אמר ליה, amar lei, that's a good question, right, we always
assume it's like הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai like all other
שיעורים, shiurim, but he's going to try to give him a more
logical reason. אמר ליה, amar lei, לפי שאי אפשר לרשות הרבים שתתלקט
במלקט וברהטני, lefi she'ee efshar lereshus harabim shetisleket bemalet uverehatni, it's impossible
with a רשות הרבים reshus harabim. that you should sort of, you
know, level it all off with like a plane and a steamroller.
He didn't say steamroller, but whatever, that's the point. It's not going
to be completely leveled. There'll be, you know, there'll be bumps in
the רשות הרבים reshus harabim, and therefore, anything within three is like,
you know, essentially the whole רשות הרבים reshus harabim, takes up that
amount of space because it moves, you know, sort of it undulates,
thank you, right, you know, it moves higher and lower. So anything
within that is essentially the same space as רשות הרבים. reshus harabim
So אי הכי, ee hachi, if that's true, so it's only about
a רשות הרבים reshus harabim, idea, but that's not true. We apply
it elsewhere. ג' נמי? gimmel nami? First of all, it should extend
even to three, not just lower than three. I mean, which is
a funny question, and how much? Three and a half, four? You
gotta cut it off somewhere. Anyway, the two, הא דתנן, ha ditnan,
how about what we taught in a משנה, המשלשל דפנות מלמעלה למטה,
hameshalshel defanos milmalah lematah, if you are making the walls of a
סוכה sukkah and you are sort of lowering them down from above
to below, ואם אין גבוהין מן הארץ שלושה טפחים, ve'im ein gevohin
min ha'aretz shelosha tefachim, if they're higher than three טפחים removed from
the ground, פסולה, psula, it's invalid. הפחות מג' כשרה, hapachas mi'gimmel kesheira,
less than three, it's okay, even though that's not a רשות הרבים.
Reshut ha-Rabim So and maybe also even though there, an implicit part
of that question could be, you need the wall to be עשרה
טפחים. asara tefachim. You don't just need it to touch the ground.
Conceptually, you need the wall to be עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, so
if your wall is only שבעה טפחים shiva tefachim and within three,
or שבעה shiva and a half and within three טפחים of the
ground, it's not enough to say it's like it's touching the ground.
Let it touch the ground, it's only שבעה טפחים. shiva tefachim. Right,
you have to conceptually extend the wall for three טפחים. So it's
a different concept than just saying it's touching the ground. So the
גמרא Gemara says, התם היינו טעמא משום דהויא לה מחיצה שהגדיין בוקעין
בה. hasam hainu ta'ama mishum dehavya lah mechitza shehagdayim bokim bah. No,
there more than three is not really, is only invalid because it
means that little goats can walk underneath it. And therefore it's a
practical issue, and less than three, goats can't walk underneath it. But
you don't really have to consider it connected or have to consider
it extending to עשרה. asara. There was a different issue, which is
still a funny answer because presumably you still need the wall to
be עשרה טפחים. asara tefachim. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara is not giving
up. The גמרא Gemara says, תינח למטה, tainach lematah, that's okay if
you're within three טפחים from below. למעלה מאי איכא למימר? lemalah mai
eika lemeimar? How about above? Which means what? If the wall is
within three טפחים of the סכך, sechach, it's like it's connected, and
there even higher because there's an idea that the wall keeps on
extending. But let's say the סכך sechach on the other plane, it's
a way, it's three טפחים removed from the wall, right? So up
to three טפחים it's like the סכך sechach is touching the wall,
more or not? How do you connect those? Where's that from? It
can't be a רשות הרבים Reshut ha-Rabim. idea. So let's take a
look. So גמרא Gemara says, אלא כל פחות משלושה כלבוד דמי הלכתא
גמירי לה. ela kol pachas mishlosha kelavud dami hilchasa gemiri lah. Fine,
it's all a tradition. So okay, so you're right, it's not based
on logic, this is just something we know by tradition. Funny that
that's, you know, here in the middle of everything else. It had
to be somewhere, I guess. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. All right. Now,
so now we discussed what? רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid? with a רשות הרבים Reshut ha-Rabim, in the middle. If
it is on the same sides of רשות הרבים Reshut ha-Rabim, and
handing over, that's a special חיוב chiyuv we learn from the לויים.
leviyim. If it's being thrown over עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, there's one
approach that says that that's... Rebbe Akiva and the rabbis debate that
as well. Can you extend the idea of handing higher than ten
טפחים to throwing higher than ten טפחים? By and large, the גמרא
Gemara rejects that, assumes that you cannot extend that. It’s a very
special case, only by handing, only by the same side of רשות
הרבים. Opposite sides of רשות הרבים, that’s where, or even opposite sides
and if you’re throwing it under ten טפחים, that’s where the debate
is. If it’s in the airspace, is it like it came to
rest or not? רבי עקיבא says yes, the rabbis say no. Part
of the חידוש chiddush that we learned is that within three טפחים,
it’s everybody would agree that you’re חייב. chayiv And if you’re carrying
it higher than ten טפחים and you stop, then you’re also חייב.
chayiv But if you’re throwing it, it’s only if it’s within ten
טפחים and that’s where the debate is. So let’s take a look
now. The גמרא Gemara does the reverse case of two רשויות הרבים
reshuyos harabim with a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid in the middle. תנו
רבנן: Tano Rabbanan: רשות הרבים לרשות הרבים רשות היחיד באמצע. reshus harabim
lereshus harabim reshus hayachid ba’emtza. From one רשות הרבים to the other
and a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, is in the middle. רבי מחייב
וחכמים פוטרים. Rebbi mechayev vachachamim potrin. רבי says you’re חייב chayiv and
the חכמים say you’re פטור. So why does רבי say you’re חייב?
chayiv רבא ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rava ushmuel damrei taveihu, they both say:
לא חייב רבי אלא ברשות היחיד מקורה. lo chiyve Rebbi ela bereshus
hayachid mekura.
He only said you’re חייב chayiv if it went through a private
domain that had a roof on it like a house, not just
like a fence around a
yard. Why? דאמרינן: damrinan: בית כמאן דמליא דמי. bayis keman demalya dami.
Conceptually what we’re saying is it’s like the house is filled, meaning
it’s a similar idea of this idea of קלוטה, kluta, you know,
caught within the airspace. So here, it’s easier to say the idea
of caught within the airspace of a house. If you’ve got a
roof on it and it’s surrounded by walls on all sides, it’s
like the thing is totally contained within this space. It’s like it’s
in a big box, as it were. So when it’s totally contained
within the space, it’s like it came to rest within the house.
But you throw through the house?
Through the house, through one window and out the other window. Right,
I’m sorry if I wasn’t clear. So you went from רשות הרבים
through one window of the house, out the other window. You were
playing ball, right? You hit the ball, it broke one window, went
out the other window, and the question is: Are you חייב chayiv
for... is it like it came to rest in the רשות היחיד?
reshus hayachid ורבי VeRebbi says yes, and the rabbis say, and the
explanation is: If it has a roof, it’s like it was completely
within a box, it’s, and therefore it’s like it came to rest
within the house.
But if it was a yard or over the roof of the
house, then no. Correct. Yeah.
So the גמרא Gemara says, רבא ושמואל, Rava ushmuel, fine, we just
did that. אבל שאינו מקורה לא. aval she’eino mekura, lo. It would...
you would not say that. Okay. אמר רב חנא אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Chana amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: מחייב היה
רבי שתים. mechayev haya Rebbi shtayim. Now, whatever the case is, fine,
it has a roof. רבי would actually say you’re חייב chayiv twice.
אחת משום הוצאה, achas mishum hotza’ah, once for going out, אחת משום
הכנסה, achas mishum hachnasah, going in. Actually the order is reversed. But
once going from רשות הרבים into the house and then from the
house out into a רשות הרבים. Okay. יתיב רב חנא וקא קשיא
ליה. Yasiv Rav Chana veka kashya lei. רב חנא Rav Chana was
sitting and discussing this and he had a problem. What's his problem?
למימרא? Lememra? To say that you’re חייב chayiv. two? That means to
say דמחייב רבי אתולדה במקום אב. de’mechayev Rebbi atoldah bimkom av. How
could you be חייב chayiv two? You’re not חייב מיתה chayav misah
twice,
you can only put somebody to death once. It means you’re חייב
chayav two קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, but how could it be two קרבנות?
korbanos? It’s the same עבירה. aveirah. Same עבירה aveirah twice is one
קרבן. korban. Ah, well one is an אב av and one's a
תולדה. toldah. Right, going to a רשות הרבים from a רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid to רשות הרבים is the אב, av, like we learned
going from the house to מחנה לויה, machaneh Leviyah, and going from
the רשות הרבים to רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid. that’s a תולדה. toldah.
So does this mean that if you do an אב av and
תולדה toldah you bring two קרבנות? korbanos? Haven’t we been teaching all
along that anything in the same category is only one קרבן? korban?
Except for רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. What? Well, right.
למימרא דמחייב רבי אתולדה במקום אב והתניא, Lememra de’mechayev Rebbi atoldah bimkom
av vehatanya, I'll prove it at least רבי would never say you
bring a תולדה, toldah, a קרבן korban for a תולדה toldah and
אב av together. רבי אומר: Rebbi omer: דברים הדברים אלה הדברים. devarim,
hadevarim, eileh hadevarim. So, you know, it says אלה הדברים אשר צוה
ה' לעשות אותם, eileh hadevarim asher tziva Hashem la’asos osam, right, when
משה Moshe gives the command of building the משכן. Mishkan. So could
it be said, so we make a דרשה drasha the way רש"י
Rashi explains it is: אלה eileh in גימטריא gematria is 36, and
because it says דברים devarim in plural that’s two more and הדברים
hadevarim gives you an extra one, gets you to 39. אלו ל"ט
מלאכות שנאמרו למשה מסיני. eileh lamed tes melachos she’ne’emru lemoshe mi’sinai. Okay
fine, that’s one of the ideas of 39. אמר ליה רב יוסף,
Amar lei Rav Yosef, so anyway, what does that say? So the
גמרא Gemara elsewhere says: why is he mentioning 39? To tell you
that 39 is the maximum number of sin offerings you can bring
because of the 39 אבות. avos. So therefore if you do an
אב av and תולדה, toldah, it’s only going to be one sin
offering because 39 is the max. All right, so we know that
רבי holds an אב ותולדה av vetoldah only once. So how could
you say that רבי would say in this case you bring two
קרבנות? korbanos? אמר ליה רב יוסף: Amar lei Rav Yosef: מר הא
מתנית לה, mar ha masnis la, you taught the idea that you’re
חייב chayav twice on this issue with רבי, וקשיא ליה דרבי אדרבי,
vekashya lei de’Rebbi ade’Rebbi, and you had a contradiction that רבי here
says you’re חייב chayav twice and it’s two types of carrying, how
could that be if רבי always says you don’t bring two קרבנות
korbanos for an אב av and a תולדה? toldah? That was your
problem. אנן אדרב יהודה מתנינן לה. anan ade’Rav Yehuda masnisan la. We
teach this idea you’re חייב chayav twice not on the statement of
רבי of throwing through a house, we teach this idea you’re חייב
chayav twice on a statement of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, ולא קשיא
לן, velo kashya lan, and therefore we don’t have a problem. What
does
that
mean? דתניא בברייתא: detanya bevrayisa: רשות היחיד לרשות הרבים ועבר ארבע אמות
ברשות הרבים. reshus hayachid lereshus harabim ve’avar arba amos bereshus harabim. Here’s
another way of
getting a twofer. Okay. Now only if you consider that it's as
if it came to stop, it's like a קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא,
keluta kemi shehuncha damya, so it's thrown into רשות הרבים, it's like
it stopped as soon as it entered. That's חיוב chiyuv number one.
Then it kept on going and then it stopped after it went
four, four אמות, amos, and that's חיוב chiyuv number
two. רבי יהודה מחייב וחכמים פוטרין. Rebbi Yehuda mechayev vechachamim potrin. רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you're חייב chayav. and the חכמים say you're
exempt. Now what does it mean חייב chayav and exempt? How could
they say you're exempt? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel, מחייב היה רבי שתים, mechayev haya Rebbi shtayim, that they're
not debating חייב chayav or not. I mean, of course you're חייב,
chayav you went from a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to רשות הרבים.
They're questioning whether you're חייב chayav twice. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda said
you're חייב chayav twice, אחת משום הוצאה, achas mishum hotza'ah, once for
bringing going from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to רשות הרבים, ואחת משום
העברה, ve'achas mishum ha'avarah, the other for going four אמות. amos. דאי
סלקא דעתך חדא הוא דמחייב, de'i salka dach-tach chada hu demechayev, if
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda was just saying you're חייב chayav once, מכלל
דרבנן פטרי לגמרי? michlal derabbanan patrei legamrei? So what, how could the
Rabbis say you're fully exempt? הא אפיק ליה מרשות היחיד לרשות הרבים.
ha afek lei mereshus hayachid lereshus harabbim. You went from a private
domain to a public domain. So clearly the question here is not
if you're חייב chayav once, but if you're חייב chayav twice because
it did two things. So you see that, so you see that
he says twice. And he says so therefore when you had this
tradition to explain that you're חייב chayav twice, it wasn't going on
רבי's statement of throwing through the house. Then you're going to have
your problem. רבי will say that an אב ותולדה av vetoladah is
only one. You don't get two קרבנות. korbanos. No, no, no, that
idea you're חייב chayav twice was said to explain this debate of
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and the רבנן Rabbanan of going into רשות
הרבים and then going four אמות amos into רשות הרבים, to say
they're debating two חיובים chiyuvim or one חיוב. chiyuv. Nobody is debating
the basic חיוב chiyuv because obviously you carry, but the question is
do you get two חיובים chiyuvim because you also did the four
אמות. amos. And here רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda would hold how about
the idea that you can't bring two קרבנות korbanos for an אב
ותולדה? av vetoladah? All right, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda wouldn't hold of
that. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda would say like רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer,
you could bring two קרבנות. korbanos.
So then you'd be חייב chayav three times if then it rolls
into רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid Yeah, but you didn't go anywhere else. It just stopped
in the. Yeah, right. If it goes. Well no because the question.
Okay, theory. Yeah, could be. Could be. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara
says, okay, so that's what, so this
idea חייב chayav, twice was said to explain this debate and the
fact that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you're חייב chayav twice isn't
a big deal. He could hold like רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, he
could hold that you bring two קרבנות korbanos for an אב ותולדה.
av vetoladah. Okay, so now the גמרא's Gemara going to discuss whether
that really is what's being debated. ממי? mimay? How do you know
they're debating two versus one? דילמא לעולם אימא לך רבי יהודה חדא
הוא דמחייב. dilma le'olam eima lach Rebbi Yehuda chada hu demechayev. Maybe
I can tell you רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says only one, ורבנן
פטרי לגמרי, verabbanan patrei legamrei, the Rabbis exempt completely. How could that
be? היכי משכחת לה? heichi mishkachas lah? What would be the scenario
that you threw something let's say from רשות היחיד into רשות הרבים
and four אמות amos in רשות הרבים and the Rabbis are still
going to say you're exempt? כגון דאמר עד דנפקא ליה לרשות הרבים
תנוח, kegon de'amar ad denafka lei lereshus harabbim tanuach, that you say
I want this to come to rest as soon as it enters
into רשות הרבים. And it didn't. It flew four אמות amos in
רשות הרבים and then came to rest. ובהא קמיפלגי, ubeha kemiflegi, this
is the debate. רבי יהודה סבר אמרינן קלוטה כמי שהונחה. Rebbi Yehuda
savar amrinan keluta kemi shehuncha. We say that when it got into
the airspace of רשות הרבים it's like it came to rest. ואיעבידה
ליה מחשבתו, ve'isavda lei machshavto, so you said you wanted it to
land within as soon as it came, and it's like it did
land because halachically it landed. ורבנן סברי לא אמרינן קלוטה כמי שהונחה.
verabbanan savrei lo amrinan keluta kemi shehuncha. The Rabbis hold we don't
say going into the airspace is like it came to rest and
דלא איעבידה ליה מחשבתו, delo isavda lei machshavto, and it did not
satisfy what your intention was. אבל בתולדה במקום אב לא מחייב רבי
יהודה. aval betoladah bemakom av lo mechayev Rebbi Yehuda. But if it
really were two חיובים, chiyuvim, a תולדה toladah and an אב, av,
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda would not say you're חייב. chayav So maybe
this debate therefore is really the Rabbis say you're fully exempt because
you wanted it to come to rest as soon as it entered
in and it did not. Now the problem with saying that debate
is is that then you wouldn't have had to say it continued
going four אמות. amos. The purpose of saying it continued going four
אמות amos is to speak about two חיובים chiyuvim from רשות היחיד
to רשות הרבים and then four אמות. amos. Here they're making it
a completely different debate which is if you say you want it
to come to rest and it didn't but do we say because
it was caught in the airspace it's like it came to rest.
Okay which by the way is a funny idea because even if
in general you hold of the principle of קלוטה כמי שהונחה, kluta
kemi shehunucha, when you're saying you want it
to come and rest you
might mean something real and physical, not just this imaginary halachic idea
that it is as if it came to rest. But that's how
the גמרא's Gemara explaining the debate and not about a question of
two versus one. So the גמרא Gemara says לא סלקא דעתך. lo
salka dach-tach. That doesn't make sense. דתניא, detanya, I'm going to prove
to you that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you can be חייב
chayav two קרבנות korbanos for a תולדה toladah and an אב. av.
דתניא רבי יהודה מוסיף אף השובט והמדקדק. detanya Rebbi Yehuda mosif af
hashoves vehamdakdek. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda added to the thirty-nine מלאכות melachos
you might remember we said that before even the case of שובט
ומדקדק shoves umedakdek which is like straightening out the threads on a
loom and banging them down after like the weave has been put
through. So אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him. שובט הרי
הוא בכלל מיסך. shovet harei hu bikhlal mesakh. No, שובט shovet is
like is a תולדה tolada of מיסך, mesakh, of setting up the
loom, ומדקדק הרי הוא בכלל אורג, umedakdek harei hu bikhlal oreg, and
מדקדק medakdek is part of the process of weaving. So those are
תולדות, tolados, those are not, you're not חייב chayav. for them. So
what is the debate? So מאי לאו דעבדינהו לתרייהו בהדי הדדי, mai
lav de'avdinehu letarveihu bahadi hadadi, presumably רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is agreeing
that they're תולדות. tolados. The גמרא Gemara doesn't want to think that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has 41 אבות. avos. So if רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is adding those two, presumably he's agreeing that they're תולדות,
tolados, and we're saying that you did both the אב av and
the תולדה, tolada, and their debate is whether you're חייב chayav twice
or you are, or you're only חייב chayav once. Are you חייב
for a תולדה במקום אב? tolada bemakom av? I know, the גמרא's
Gemara going to say this. ושמע מינה מחייב היה רבי יהודה תולדה
במקום אב. ushma mina mechayev haya Rabbi Yehuda tolada bemakom av. And
therefore you see he's חייב for תולדה tolada and an אב, av,
because that, and because the scenario would be exactly that, that he's
describing doing a תולדה tolada and an אב av and saying two,
and the Rabbis are saying only one. גמרא says ממאי? mimai? Since
when? Who says? דילמא לעולם דעבדה להא לחודא והא לחודא. dilma le'olam
de'avdah leha lachuda veha lachuda. Forget it, you did each one individually.
We're not talking about any special case of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
א תולדה במקום אב לא מחייב, a tolada bemakom av lo mechayev,
and he would say if you did the תולדה tolada and the
אב av together, you're not חייב. So what's this issue about this,
about this שובט ומדקדק? shovet umedakdek? What it sounds like, ובהא קמיפלגי,
ubeha kamiflagi, this is what they debate. רבי יהודה סבר הני אבות
נינהו. Rabbi Yehuda savar hani avos ninhu. He says there are 41
אבות. avos. These are two extra אבות. avos. רבנן סברי הני תולדות
נינהו. Rabbanan savri hani tolados ninhu. These are תולדות, tolados, which is
exactly what it sounds like. תדע, teda, and you know this is
true, דקתני רבי יהודה מוסיף, dekatani Rabbi Yehuda mosif, like Michael said.
It says רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda added the following two. אי אמרת
בשלמא אבות, i amarta bishlama avos, if we're talking about what are
the אבות, avos, מאי מוסיף? mai mosif? What does it mean he
added? מוסיף אבות. mosif avos. He added the אבות, avos, these two
as, as two extra אבות. avos. אלא אי אמרת תולדות, ela i
amarta tolados, but if it's just תולדות tolados and the question is
nobody's debating the category, the only question is: are you חייב once
or חייב twice? So מאי מוסיף? mai mosif? What does it mean
he added? He should have said חייב שתים. chayav shtayim. מוסיף mosif
means he's adding a new category. Okay. So, here's a question about,
we had a teaching, just to remind you how we got here.
We had a teaching that in a certain case of carrying, somebody
would actually be מחייב you twice. Which means, conceptually, that you could
say you're חייב a תולדה במקום אב, tolada bemakom av, because or
else it's all, all the same. Where was this taught? One approach
is to say it was taught by רבי of throwing something in
the house and from the house it went back out to the
other side of to another street. So when רבי says it's like
it came to rest in the house, you would also say you're
חייב twice. Fine, that could work conceptually, but the problem is that
רבי is one of the classic positions who says that when you
do a תולדה tolada and an אב av together you're only חייב
once. So then the response is, it's not about רבי, that idea
חייב twice is about this debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
the רבנן Rabbanan when you threw it from a רשות היחיד to
רשות הרבים and then it continued going four אמות. amos. And there
it's a question of are you חייב twice or once? And that's
why we described it as two מלאכות. melachos. First it entered רשות
הרבים and then it went for four אמות, amos, and that's the
question: are you חייב twice or once? And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would say you could be חייב twice. The גמרא tries to push
back and says, no no no, maybe the Rabbis say you're totally
פטור because it didn't, wasn't exactly what you intended. Okay. But that's
the question of how to interpret that debate. And now we end
with this issue about what happens when it is, it's not exactly
what you intended. So the גמרא says, ולמאי דסלקא דעתך מעיקרא דמחייב
האי רבי יהודה שתים, ulemai desalka datakh me'ikara demachayev hai Rabbi Yehuda
shtayim, now if according to the approach that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would say twice, once for entering רשות הרבים and then for going
four אמות amos in רשות הרבים, so one minute, how could you
have done that? אי להכא קא בעי לה, i lehacha ka ba'ei
la, if you wanted it in place number one, if you wanted
it to come to rest when it entered רשות הרבים, להכא לא
קא בעי לה. lehacha lo ka ba'ei la. You didn't want it
in place number two, where it went four אמות amos later. אי
להכא קא בעי לה, i lehacha ka ba'ei la, and if you
wanted it in place number two where the four אמות amos into
רשות הרבים is where you wanted it to come to rest, להכא
לא קא בעי לה, lehacha lo ka ba'ei la, then you didn't
want it in place number one when it entered רשות הרבים. How
do you get two חיובים? chiyuvim? Right? Two חיובים chiyuvim means you
wanted both acts as separate acts. Here you wanted it in one
of those two places, so how do you get it twice? So
the גמרא says, אמר ליה באומר כל מקום שתרצה תנוח. amar lei
be'omer kol makom shetirtze tanu'ach. I really don't care where it lands.
I want to get it into רשות הרבים, I don't care where
it lands. So since you don't care, since in practice, הלכתית halakhically
we will say that two acts occurred. By the way, what's also
shocking here, whether it's רבי throwing through the house or whether it's
this case into רשות הרבים, we define it as two acts even
though you did not initiate at all the second act. Meaning, it
was a continuous motion, right? This thing flying into רשות הרבים and
we now הלכתית halakhically will come and say two acts took place.
It entered רשות הרבים, קלוטה כמי שהונחה, it was in the air
space, it like came to rest, act number one. Then although it
was continuous motion, right, then it moved from that coming to rest,
that imaginary coming to rest which we have superimposed on it when
it entered the air space, and then it went four more אמות
amos and then fell down, and now we're going to say that
was act number two. And since you didn't care what happened to
it, then you are going to be חייב for two according to
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That's at least what we were suggesting when
we said there would be two חיובים. chiyuvim. Yes? Right, normally for
a מלאכה, melacha, it's a creative act and you have to have
intention for a particular result. I guess this is an exception? Oh...
No, if you were digging let's say, I mean, digging a hole.
Oh, you're saying why without the intention for that result? Yeah. Well,
no, we have an intention for something otherwise, like if I'm digging
a hole and I'm trying to get the dirt. But let's say
I'm digging a hole and I'm not trying to, you know, I'm
just having fun, I'm like just enjoying like you know the experience
or whatever, I'm not thinking of producing a hole, right? So, although
maybe at a certain level you can call it מתעסק. Mit'ase. But
like, you know, you know that it- having a certain absence of
כוונה Kavana as opposed to opposite כוונה Kavana is not such a
חידוש. chiddush. The bigger חידוש chiddush here is, and this is what
the next סוגיא Sugya begins, and maybe we'll just start reading it,
is the idea that by carrying, you know, again, the question is
do you have this degree of precision by other מלאכות? Melachot? By
carrying we say it- it has to go where you wanted it
to go, okay? So and therefore if you remember from one rooftop
to the next, like we said earlier, if it fell down, it
wouldn't have been that you did it בשוגג. b'shogeg. You wouldn't have
done the מלאכה, Melakha, you didn't want it to fall down. Here,
unless we say that you explicitly say, I don't care where it
goes, if you intended it to go in one place, you can't
be חייב twice if it went in a different place, it's not
your act. So particularly by carrying we see this high emphasis on
exactly the way you intended it to happen. You might remember we
taught earlier, if you were carrying it and wanted to carry it
in front of you and it flipped behind you, that's enough to
exempt you. Okay, so this is the idea that- that we've laid
out in a few places, and now let's begin to read the
next discussion, which actually talks about this question of the precision of
your כוונה Kavana particularly when it comes to carrying. So the גמרא
says like this: פשיטא it's obvious to me that נתכוון לזרוק שמונה
וזרק ארבע. niskaven lizrok shmona v'zarak arba. You wanted to throw something
eight אמות Amot in רשות הרבים and it only went four and-
eight אמות Amot and it only went four אמות. Amot. That you're
הרי כתב שם משמעון. harey katav Shem mi-Shimon. It's obvious to me
you'd be חייב, because if you want to throw it eight, included
in eight is four. So that's like I wanted to write the
name שמעון Shimon and I stopped at the מם, Mem, I- I'm
חייב because part of writing the name שמעון Shimon is writing the
words- is the name- it's the שין מם, Shin-Mem, שם. Shem. So
obviously I'd be חייב if I wanted to go eight and went
four, that's included in my intent. נתכוון לזרוק ארבע וזרק שמונה מאי?
Niskaven lizrok arba v'zarak shmona mai? What about the opposite? I wanted
to throw four and it went eight. So it was more than
I intended, am I חייב or not? So the גמרא says: מי
אמרינן- mi amrinan should we say האפיק ליה? ha-apik lei? You took
it out. Now that's a funny word, אפיק, apik, took out. What
did you take it out from? It was all in רשות הרבים.
But that might be the point. When you say four אמות Amot
in רשות הרבים, one way to conceptualize that is not that four
אמות Amot is an arbitrary quantifiable amount, but that four אמות Amot
is considered your space. So, or the object's space. And when you
take it four אמות, Amot, you've removed it from its original space.
So if we emphasize that idea of removing it from its original
space, then maybe it doesn't matter so much whether it went four
אמות Amot or eight אמות. Amot. You wanted to move it four
אמות, Amot, it did, you took it out of its space, maybe
you'd be חייב. או דלמא Odilma or do we say היכא דבעי
לא נח, heicha d'baei lo nach, where you wanted it to land
after four אמות Amot it didn't, it landed further, eight אמות. Amot.
So the גמרא says: one minute, ולאו היינו דאמר ליה רבינא לרב
אשי, v'lav hainu d'amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, isn't this what רבינא
Ravina said to רב אשי? Rav Ashi? ואמר ליה באומר כל מקום
שתתרצה תנוח. V'amar lei b'omer kol makom she-tirtze tanuach. We just got
through saying the case above, you know, when it was flying through
רשות הרבים, the only way you'd be חייב twice if you explicitly
say I don't care where it comes to land. And now what
the גמרא is actually saying and with this we will pick up
tomorrow is that a minute ago we just said that if in
reality it did multiple things but you did not have specific acceptable
כוונה Kavana for it to do, you would be exempt. So here
too if it's not exactly the way you intended you would actually
be exempt even though one act might have included the other act.
So this is what I started to sort of leave you hanging
but it's too much to rush for now so this is what
we will pick up tomorrow this question about when it actually did
you intended one thing it did more or less what you intended
either a subset or a superset of what you intended, are you
still going to be חייב or specifically by carrying is it only
with very precise כוונה? Kavana? And we'll pick up with that tomorrow.